hello and welcome this is octave guest
stream number 32.1
it's January 10 2023 we're here with
Adam peace and we will be hearing a
presentation followed by a discussion so
Adam thank you very much for joining
today looking forward to this and off to
you
okay thanks very much for having me uh
looking forward to presenting a few bits
of initial research as well as some
background on long-term ongoing Research
into understanding language and trying
to mimic some just some elements of
human thought everything I do is open
source so I've got some links for you
there I also have a pretty active
YouTube channel although it's been a
little quiet lately so there's a lot of
material here that I won't be able to go
into in depth and so I'm eager to answer
questions when we get to the question
period and also would encourage folks to
take a look at that channel where
there's
longer video format presentations about
a whole host of topics that we'll
probably touch on today
so I have a large ontology I'll explain
in a minute what I mean by an ontology
that's called Sumo uh and I'm also going
to reference some work that Facebook has
done called their baby Corpus so that's
the background for the cartoons that I'm
showing you
the main topic that I want to cover
today is a notion of Common Sense Auto
formalization my objective is to be able
to make statements in human natural
language just in English at the moment
uh ask questions also in natural
language and get answers but get answers
with explanation something that uh
modern question answering systems that
we hear about each day in the popular
press are generally not capable of doing
you might get an answer but you don't
know why and and knowing why and
understanding and explanation is very
important
so we're not talking about just
information retrieval we're not talking
about Google where you ask a question
and you get a list of documents in which
there might be an answer or even
Google's occasional capabilities for
very specific sorts of questions where
they give you an answer but they'll
never tell you why it's more like you
know you ask what's the weather today
you get a nice concise link to the
weather but you won't get an explanation
for why the weather is what it is
so what do I mean by ontology are you
meaning to share we see the first slide
you're still only seeing the first slide
okay I'm on slide three so let's go back
to I'm not sure why that's no interest
showing up but uh good it looks good now
Common Sense we'll stick with this
format then instead of the slide
presentation format thank you it looks
good okay so here's what I just talked
about
um so let me give you my definition for
what is an ontology because this is a
word that at a certain point in recent
history maybe about a decade or two ago
got overloaded so much now that just
about anything is called an ontology and
so for me to distinguish ontology from
things we already had words for like
semantic Network or schema I consider an
ontology to be essentially a dictionary
for computers to read and that also
requires a bit of unpacking what is a
dictionary for computers to read well
for me it means minimally we've got to
have terms a set of terms that that
label things in our world but most
importantly we have to have a set of
definitions that are stated in a
computable language so just stating
things in English or French that are
definitions for words well that's a
dictionary it's not an ontology
and if we don't have definitions in a
some sort of mathematical language or
programming language of some sort then
our machines are only going to have the
barest abilities to manipulate or do
things with those natural language
definitions so I think they have to be
in a formal language to nail down
meanings that we have shared meaning so
we have shared meaning between people
that that agree to use a particular
ontology and maybe more importantly we
have shared meaning between people and
computers so that the same constraints
the same inferences that people would be
able to make with these terms the
computer is also able to make because of
these mathematically expressed
definitions so that's what I've spent
the last 22 years trying to build up and
this is work that draws on Linguistics
philosophy and computer science as well
as logic as a sub-discipline of of
probably all of those three 3.
and one reason I'm doing this nowadays
artificial intelligence has become
almost synonymous with machine learning
so I need to just to explain a little
bit well why am I doing this this is
sort of old-fashioned AI of writing down
lots of rules why do we still need to do
this well I'm a big fan of Daniel
kahneman's work and this is just one
justification of many but hopefully
because it's very well articulated in
his work I hopefully this can be at
least the start of a justification for
some of you who might be unfamiliar with
the this symbolic approach that used to
be the primary approach in artificial
intelligence
I think that he makes a good case that
humans have two modes of thought we have
an instinctive intuitive sensory pattern
matching kind of process that's good for
face or voice recognition or making a
very snap judgment about what to do in a
particular situation uh that is you know
learned from the presentation of many
many similar situations and that sort of
mode of thought fits very well with
statistically based machine learning
neural network steep neural networks and
so forth that's an important part of
intelligence and it's led to a lot of
important uh commercial activities but
there is another mode of intelligence
that uh Professor Kahneman I think
illustrates quite clearly that is a
slower more deliberative deductive
approach where people can explain what
they do as opposed to just give a
reaction and it seems like in large
parts of the AI Community people are
starting to recognize that yes there is
still this this set of things that we
require our computers to do that they're
not doing very well with the current
neuros
neural approach
um
Merrick approach that we need another
mode of tool set for and so we're
starting to see this keyword
neurosymbolic approach of trying to
balance uh statistical machine learning
approaches with some sort of explicit
representation in a symbolic form and
it's this latter bit that I've been
doing a lot of work with and I think
it's the combination of these two of
main approaches that's going to lead us
to some more exciting capability that's
just my assessment of the state of the
field but there is some emerging
evidence that this in fact is the case
that we have a potential with
integrating these two approaches to
handle a broader range of things that
would look a lot more like human
intelligence
along with this Grand goal of doing AI
I've also been applying uh this work in
creating this large dictionary to some
far more prosaic stuff in data
integration the bulk of the commercial
Consulting work that I've been doing
really over the past 10 years
is just looking at a software
engineering methodology of trying to
capture the formal meaning of things
that we use in computer science
databases spreadsheets and so forth you
know anytime you have a spreadsheet you
usually have a column a set of columns
across the top of your spreadsheet that
has some labels and it's very unusual
for people to have any sort of explicit
definitions of what those labels
actually mean it's usually just assumed
that people by looking at those labels
you know if you're in the same Community
or you can ask for an explanation that
gives you a good sense of what are
what's the intended semantics of that
particular column based on that
particular label and what I found is
that you know it might work for a
spreadsheet where you've got a few dozen
columns and you're working closely with
with some long time colleagues but as
soon as you get to a larger organization
with a larger set of symbols labels
where people may be working at different
locations maybe they've never even met
each other where there's uh uh
interactions occurring over the space of
years in large multinational
corporations that people's initial
assumptions about how clear their labels
are are usually completely wrong and so
people wind up using data in
dramatically different ways inconsistent
with its original intent precisely
because nobody's taken the time to
actually Define things and even in the
rare cases of organizations that do have
data dictionaries that that Define their
terms the intended meaning of their
terms they tend to Define them in very
informal ways using natural language
definitions which means then that the
machines can do very little to help
ensure that people's intended
specification of semantics is consistent
across a large body of terms you might
be able to have a human being keep a
data dictionary of 100 terms consistent
and well-organized uh over time over a
long period of time but once you get two
thousands or tens of thousands of terms
it's well beyond human capacity to keep
such a product consistent you need
Automation and unless you have uh
definitions that are explicit and in a
computable language the computer can do
very little to help keep those
definitions consistent so that's one of
the big byproducts of all of this work
so far and I use techniques like
automated they're improving but you know
I don't have time to talk about now but
would love to talk about it in in detail
for anyone who's interested to keep
these definitions consistent so I have a
logical approach for the semantics of
terms lexical semantics the the
semantics of the words we use and this
extends also to sort of computer science
constructs like labels for tables or
columns or
database elements and so forth
right and this is useful anywhere pretty
much anyone has a spreadsheet anyone has
a database this is a something that uh
people don't realize they could make use
of people seem to accept that uh they're
gonna need to have a lot of human to
human to communication to explain the
meanings of terms and there's just
another way right and that's what I've
developed and that's what I'm basing
this work on language understanding on
there's a common belief that oh this is
just too hard right
um that we should be able to come up
with these things easily there's too
much of them meanings change and so
forth
once you you take the perspective that
there is a need for uh precise semantics
for our labels and that this precise
semantics uh is something like
definition definition in a dictionary
but in a formal language
then it's not just a sort of a graph or
a list of relationships or likelihoods
or or probabilities
um it's it's starts to be hard to
imagine then how a machine would just
come up with this sort of thing
automatically and of course we have
another another venue in which we take
this sort of harder approach of
programming and don't expect machines to
just do everything automatically and
that's programming right we have many
many millions of programmers in the
world now it's they're expensive it is a
time-consuming process to program things
but we invest in this because there
simply isn't another way to do it and we
we make this Enterprise of programming
feasible through a couple of of points
one is having very rich languages so we
can say everything that we want to say
so we don't want to be restricted in the
sort of programs we can write similarly
we need to make sure we're not
restricted in the sorts of definitions
that we can write and the way that we
make that practical is through reuse
your modern programmer if you deliver
some software you're you're writing
maybe one percent of the program one
percent of the code that's delivered
most of what you deliver is going to be
a set of large libraries and reusable
components operating system database
a web server and any number of other
things the Java collection classes numpy
libraries if you're doing python the way
in which modern software development is
practical is through reuse and so that's
the other thing that I've been working
to provide is this thing called Sumo
which is a library of definitions that
can be reused that take this problem
that many people would otherwise
consider to be completely intractable
manual creation of knowledge and makes
it eminently practical because you're
actually reusing most of your semantics
by virtue of using this Library
right so this uh Sumo like sumo wrestler
suggested upper merged ontology started
in the year 2000 it started as just an
upper ontology so the the acronym is a
bit of a misnomer a bit of an
anachronism if you will right now that
it's really a comprehensive ontology not
just an upper ontology because it's
grown to be about 20 000 terms eighty
thousand uh handwritten statements in an
expressive higher order mathematical
logic it includes links to vast fact
bases like the Iago system lots of
translations from its authored format
into some of the standard
representations used in the automated
theorem to proven community and as I
mentioned it's all open source and
online and every version has been open
source there's nothing that's hailed
back for commercial reasons
uh let me mention wordnet so another
common misconception in ontology is that
we have to use words and follow the
definitions of words and as as we should
all know words are ambiguous
um and words are polysemous the same
word can have multiple meanings so we've
created a very uh clear division but
also a relationship between the senses
the concepts that we have in the world
that have formal definitions and the
labels that we as humans put on those
Concepts to communicate them to each
other and this also makes it easy to
ensure that orientology is not tied to
any particular one language because as
we any one of us who's who's
multilingual knows an English word and a
Tagalog word can have the same
underlying semantics the same underlying
real world referent but we use different
labels and so we need to make sure that
we can have vocabularies that are mapped
to our common single formal ontology
that tries to explain and Define
Concepts in our world and not let sort
of language and labels and intuitions
about those labels creep into our formal
definition so we reuse Princeton's
wordnet which is a project going on for
about 30 years now I think and it has
also projections into multiple languages
polish word net Tagalog wordnet for
example uh here is uh there's continuing
work on that from uh which I'm very
excited because I started a Tagalog word
net back uh in the 2000s at De La Salle
University and so it's great to see that
that assertive effort continuing there's
word nets for Arabic and Chinese and you
know many other languages and so keep
those labels in English those
dictionaries human dictionaries distinct
but related to the formal inventory of
mathematically expressed Concepts and so
back in the early 2000s we took an
effort to go through all 117
000 sin sets in wordnet all 117
000 linguistically labeled Concepts and
map them all to Sumo one at a time by
hand it's just an enormous effort where
we couldn't have really done it
automatically it required human
inspection we invested that effort and
it since paid off for the linguistic
work that we do with this ontology
why do we need both well the formal
definitions are things that just aren't
inward net or any other dictionary you
might have a word for earlier and a
natural language definition for what it
means for some events to be earlier than
another but we need a precise
mathematical logical definition of what
earlier means and so Sumo has this and
many many other axioms that individually
are trivial but together add up to
creating a certain understanding about
the world that without it machines just
don't have we need a machine to know
that if one event is earlier than
another that the end point of this first
event is before the beginning point of
the second event
so we've got a formal mathematical
definition of earlier which you just
don't have in a dictionary this allows
machine to do logic inference automated
inference and and give you conclusions
and explain those conclusions not a
criticism of wordnet just they're
different products with different needs
and we need both
also I get a lot of uh of questions
about what kind of logic do we need do
we really need a very complicated
expressive logic it's very popular
nowadays for people to use taxonomies or
knowledge graphs well knowledge graphs
are essentially semantic networks it's a
knowledge representation that was
created back really in the 1960s and so
it does surprise me that it's kind of
you know what's old is New Again in
artificial intelligence somehow and that
that knowledge graphs are a big thing
now but it's a knowledge representation
technology that leaves out a lot of
stuff that we would need to say about
the real world in order to define the
terms that we use so natural language
definitions aren't enough and we believe
that defining our our terms or our
Concepts is good which particular
language do we choose and I've had
people often say you know with usually
with really without any backup oh those
are the rare cases well I got frustrated
with that so I did a a paper recently
right well now almost two years old
about trying to quantify how often do we
use constructs in language that require
more than just a graph of relationships
and so I came up with some statistics I
don't I'm not going to go into this
paper in great detail but if you're
interested I'd love to follow up with
you and I came up with that in two uh
looking at two large corpora Brown
Corpus is kind of old and kind of small
by modern standards but I also use the
Corpus of Contemporary American English
took a random sample of sentences uh
created an automated system for looking
at some various features that require in
language a translation into using an
expressive logic such as modal
Expressions can May should might or
expressions of authorship you know said
wrote
epistemic knows believes these are words
in language that trigger the need for a
more expressive representation we can
also I could give you a lot of detail on
why that's directly entailed this is not
just a you know this is not just my
opinion trying to to Advocate a more
expressive of logic these are very sort
of strict things that are well known in
linguistics but at least now it's well
Quantified that about 50 percent of
statements taken from a random sample of
a large Corpus do actually require these
more expressive semantics so I think
I've made a strong case that we can't
just get away with graphs unless we want
to leave out about half of the things
that people say to each other and that
tells me that that we really need this
as more expressive logic
okay so so that's all the Preamble what
is that was the the library of semantics
of meaning that I already have and how
can I use that now to try to create a
system and this is research right and
it's uh relatively experimental even at
the moment
that the attempt is to try to create a
system where the machine can translate
automatically
from English sentences into a formal
precise semantics using these terms out
of the ontology that themselves are
precisely defined
so I have the one at the starting point
uh English statements or questions
I translate these things to logic I want
to be able to send them to a powerful
theorem prover that's at least first
order logic plus equality but preferably
higher order logic so I can handle some
of these modal Expressions there are a
few such provers
and I want it to engage in its process
of doing theorem proving not only with
the statements and the question that a
particular user has provided at one time
but also this Rich background that
describes the world so that the machine
is not just doing you know a sort of
simple matching even with these powerful
tools but it's really taking into
account background knowledge World
Knowledge in the same way that a that a
person would and then when it's done
when it's got an answer I want it to be
able to explain what it does and Theorem
provers have this or capability already
it's built in they were designed to
provide proofs because a lot of the work
in fear improving is for fear improving
in advanced mathematics so there's a
quiet but significant community of
mathematicians and computer scientists
that are using automated they're
improving to prove novel theorems in
mathematics and because they're in
mathematics they have a very strict
standard of what constitutes a real work
you have to show a proof just like
almost all of us probably experienced in
high school geometry of proving one
triangle is the same as another through
maybe the side angle side process
machines can now do this and much more
significant and complicated and
sophisticated sorts of proofs and
provide detailed uh breakdown of how it
reached its conclusion and I take this
as to being something that's required if
you ask another person what's the answer
to question X okay they give you y as an
answer but then you want to know yeah
what's the detail how did you come to
that conclusion it's not just enough to
say well I told you so so believe me
sometimes you might get away with that
but not all the time especially not for
anything that's that's complicated and
so our machine should be able to do that
as well
so I've done a number of forays into
this Grand goal over the course of my
career I started out with something
called controlled English to logic
translation where I had a hand-built
grammar of a small subset of English
that was designed to be unambiguous it
was all written in prologue and I was
able to create expressions using Sumo
terms in its logic which was mostly
first order logic back then in the early
2000s and it was you know somewhat
somewhat successful but it was a fairly
restricted subset of English and so the
parser would break and say syntax error
all too often and that was kind of
frustrating
um it was sort of like what one
experiences today with something like
Alexa or or Google where you ask a
question says I'm sorry I don't
understand right and so people wind up
self self governing their uh their uh
utterances to adapt to the machine and
people were able to do that with my kelp
system but it's still kind of
frustrating I'd like to be able to
handle text that was written not for
that particular system and not dumbed
down on the Fly by a human but rather
any arbitrary sort of text so then I
started working with Stanford's core NLP
system and using dependency parse uh
Transformations and trying to turn
dependency parses into logic I did have
some success with that but I found that
even as good as machine learning based
statistical parsers are there's still a
lot of cases where they bring breakdown
in fact
they they give a lot of metrics that
look very encouraging usually on a per
word or per symbol basis and they'll say
or it were 97 percent correct on uh
unlabeled attachment score is one that's
used in the dependency parsing community
and that sounds like a very high
percentage but in a your average
sentence in English is depending on you
know who you talk to what uh how you how
you collect the statistics about 24
words
well if you look at uh 97 percent raised
to the 24th power
um then you get a problem and you get
actually less than 50 of your sentences
are going to be parsed correctly and
again that's unlabeled attachment score
for dependency parses that merely means
that two words are found to have the
same dependency relation without a
commitment to what exactly that relation
is well you need the label Detachment
score which of course is lower and you
need it to be correct for all of these
words to every really a coherent
understanding of a sentence if you're
going to do any sort of automatic
translation so although this the systems
are good and they've certainly gotten
better from 2015 I mean Stanford stanza
is is yet another you know a few
percentage points better than core NLP
was in terms of its dependency parsing
but it's still not reliable enough not
consistent not stable enough uh for me
to use that as a basis for translation
and then there was all the problem of
well how do I actually take that that
output and reliably create logic from it
and that meant at that time I was doing
a hand-built rule base and it just
didn't work in the limit it was
encouraging I think there's potential if
you had enough people working on it a
bit more research but it wasn't the way
in which I thought I could reach success
so I'm doing something different now so
I'm I'm doing what I guess is more
prevalent now in machine learning than
instead of doing a pipeline of machine
learning operations trying to do
everything all at once with
extraordinarily large corpora uh where I
am trying to train a system uh to do
auto formalization of language to go
straight from language to logic without
any intermediate approach like
dependency parsing and this is based on
some of the success uh with my colleague
Joseph Urban who's been doing this for
sort of work for mathematics
so one of the challenges of using uh
Fair improvers automated theorem
proofers for mathematics is that as
formal as mathematics is it's not really
quite formal enough in a mathematics
textbook there's still a lot of text and
there's still a lot of things that
aren't themselves precisely defined and
there's also a lot of stuff there in
mathematics that's not in a common and
computable format so for a long time
there's been this problem of how do we
take mathematical textbooks and turn
them into extraordinarily detailed
formalizations that an automated theorem
prover can handle in first order logic
plus equality or some other kind of
mathematical logic so Joseph has had
considerable success at this and we
decided to team up on trying to do an
even this even harder problem of just
looking at unrestricted texts not just
mathematics
and they've been using uh Google's
neural machine translation system which
is built on top of tensorflow where at
the moment using kind of a relatively
old version of that we tried a newer
version it turned out to actually be
slower for our purposes but uh we need
to do a lot more experimentation and
make this work more popular so people
tell us where we're going wrong and
maybe there's some better machine
learning libraries that we could use for
this
so this is the the architecture now I
want to tell you a bit more about how we
actually come up with this set of
natural language logic pairs because you
know like other work of this sort the
libraries of pairs of your input output
pairs that you're trying to train has to
be really really big you know orders of
magnitude bigger than any sort of
pipeline approach because you're trying
to tackle the whole problem hand-hand
and there's a lot more variability your
statistical significance for the
appearance of any given feature
correlated with any other given feature
is is really low he has a very long tail
in language of things that are not seen
too often so your Corpus has to be very
big how do we get that Corpus we
certainly not feasible to translate a
lot of English by hand into logic so how
do we get this thing to begin with
so we were aware of this project done at
Facebook called the baby Corpus in part
because uh tomash mikolov has returned
to his home country of the Czech
Republic and now works with Yosef Urban
at CTU Prague so we had a benefit of
getting some of his perspective on this
work it was basically an effort to try
to teach machines how to do simple
inferences and we'll look at some of
those simple inferences in a moment and
in order to do that they tried to
generate a very large synthetic data set
of natural simple natural language
sentences and simple natural language
inferences that they wanted the machines
to be able to train up to handle
um this ultimately they used really only
a few sort of rules or patterns I think
tomasia said there's something like 20
different patterns I've looked at the
code it's written in Lua it wouldn't be
hard to rewrite it in a sort of more
more common language I think it's not
particularly complicated code not a huge
code base a lot of simple patterns a
great idea but I think we can do better
at it given the resources that Sumo
provides for Generation as well as
understanding and anchoring meaning
right so they had a lot of their
knowledge representation such as it is
was things like you know you have a
bedroom a thing a location actors uh
existing in this world it sort of harks
back to uh the blocks world of uh
Patrick Henry Winston uh
I think it was Winston hope I've got
that reference right you know back in
the 70s uh there's this notion that we
could do uh there's a system called uh
sure glue I think it was that did
operations in a world of blocks so a
constrained World there were actors
there were a few things that could be
manipulated and the system was able to
understand very simple utterances well
they've kind of turned this on its head
created a knowledge representation for a
certain world and then tried to generate
a lot of sentences from it to create
this synthetic model of things that a
machine should be able to to do
inferences about
and so here's some of the content of
their questions so Fred is either in the
school or the park uh Mary went back to
the office is Mary in the office so the
first sentence is just a confusion uh uh
element of of the the Corpus it's really
if Mary went back to the office yes
she's in the office uh bill is either in
the kitchen or the park another
confusion sense Fred moved to the cinema
it's Fred in the park well no he's not
in the park but park has been seen as a
token earlier and so they wanted to make
sure that the automated learning system
isn't just con uh trying to find
proximity
is a good thing to include in their data
set
so lots of stuff like this and more
complicated things also just presented
really some of the most simple examples
but all generated from a very simple
knowledge model
Concepts that weren't really defined and
a massive presentation of tiny very
mind-numbingly tiny variations in a wide
variety of sentences
so we started out thinking well let's
just cover this the stuff that's in the
baby Corpus so we understand what
they're doing and the big advantage that
we thought we could bring to this is we
don't have to learn logic you know in a
way they were they had a simple Corpus
that was trying to accomplish something
that's very hard which was to teach
machines just through massive examples
how to do logical inferences or a
certain subset of logical inferences we
have an easier problem if we use a fear
improver we don't have to teach of the
system to do logical inference we
already have that
we just need to get the knowledge
representation from English into logic
and then let the theorem proofers do
their thing
so again very simple World they had
objects locations actors States actions
a few other decorations
and so we tried to figure out really
what they meant in a way that was hard
because they didn't have a distinction
between instances and classes so uh you
know we can talk about in Sumo
relationship that in an action one thing
is an object transferred from one
location to another they have this
notion of being gettable which is really
a modal and so we had to figure out what
what did they mean they didn't really
mean a modal uh they meant yeah some
something that can be transferred and
then there has to be some kind of
transferred example we wound up
interpreting a lot of their symbols not
as classes so the notion of an apple is
a class but the Apple it gets
transferred in a particular sentence is
an instance so this difference between
existential and Universal
quantifications so we'd create a term
like apple one is a kind of apple is an
instance of an apple
right and that's a getable thing and
it's located in a particular area Etc so
I don't have a lot of time to go into
our knowledge representation but uh if
you want a full course on Sumo I can do
that at some point and there's a lot of
videos online also so maybe I'll skip
through a little bit of this uh we
wanted to make sure we covered you know
all of their stuff uh you know we did
they they referred to things like
chocolate and milk and garden and
container and box and we actually had
all this in Sumo so getting back to this
notion of well if you had to Define all
this stuff from scratch you'd be tempted
just like the Facebook guys did to just
use the labels and assume everything
everybody means the same thing but we
didn't have to do that we already had
these terms precisely defined in Sumo
and we're able just to reuse them so we
did a big table this is just a portion
of that table of all the different
things that they referred to that we
already had or in some a few cases
didn't have and we needed to add them
but even you know adding the new
Concepts and their definitions easy
because the new Concepts had definitions
that were based on in turn other terms
we already had so we just had to combine
them in the right ways
you know we we didn't take for granted
uh the that we were just using the first
meaning of things for example they had
the word pajamas in some of their
database well pajamas have a couple of
meanings in the dictionary yeah I wasn't
all that familiar with the second
meaning but it does exist and so we want
to make sure we're using the right
meaning so we also did mappings to
wordnet of the terms we defined so that
we had disambiguation potential for our
natural language
uh there are a number of things because
of this uh small and artificial World
they they had uh inferences like if
you're hungry uh then essentially you go
to the kitchen and eat something that's
in the kitchen that doesn't really hold
in the real world obviously we're don't
we're not in this fantasy constrained
world that uh hunger immediately entails
you go to the kitchen and eat an apple
um but so we had to create some kind of
some bogus rules in Sumo that were very
specific just to this Corpus to try to
replicate the inferences that they were
doing so here's a here's the rule that
gives the right answer for this Corpus
uh it gets a little complicated to State
it but we can state it in Sumo that if
you have a cognitive agent that's hungry
and that's at a particular time then
there's a translocation event uh or that
is desired by that agent and that
translocation has a destination of the
kitchen where there's a getting a of an
apple
okay a rule that that doesn't belong to
be in Sumo uh on any permanent basis but
is what's used to cover the semantics of
this particular Corpus
and we looked at things like being bored
and tired which they had they all say if
you're bored and tired you go to sleep
okay that's I wish that that were true
for all of us hard-working Engineers
that we had that option we don't at all
times but that was what covered the
semantics of the Corpus so we had to do
similar things for bored and tired
um they don't really have weights and
measures and units in the baby ontology
Sumo of course has detailed ontology of
weights and measures of units all the
system international
measures and we had to figure out how we
were going to translate these hacks that
were in this Corpus of you know things
have a numerical size one two or three
something like that how are we going to
represent that so we figured out a
similar hack for covering that
all right so you know we we did this
exploration to make sure that uh we
could cover one of these sample worlds
but what we really want to do is
generate a much larger corpus with a
more interesting more varied set of
things that are referred to in the real
world
so we wanted to do uh a synthetic text
generation as our first step so that we
kind of seed this system long term we
know that we need to go beyond that
synthetic test we're not there yet we're
just still in this in the process of
creating this very large set of
synthetic sentences because we can start
with an idea or a knowledge
representation about what we want to
express in the world and generate logic
syntactically and semantically valid
logic expressions from that while at the
same time because we've created the the
state of the world artificially in a
program we can then also create a
sentence that models that state of the
world so we go kind of both both
directions both to logic and language
from a very ad hoc sort of expression in
some Java code about what's true in the
real world
connect allows us to do a lot of
variation but it's never going to cover
the full expressivity of natural
language but we think it will cover
enough that it gives us a head start
where we can then start seeing well
where does our automatic language to
logic system break down what are the
sentences where it fails where it
generates something that's not even
syntactically correct maybe or Circa or
violates constraints that we know from
sumo about how the world works and then
try to add those as new patterns to our
generation system so we can find one
sentence that causes a problem we look
at the area the the core issue of what
causes the problem and look at you know
maybe the things that are variable this
sentence so we might have a sentence
that's problematic that has some sub
subject and an object where the subjects
and the objects have a wide varieties
that could things that could be
substituted in that we can turn into
sort of a template to try to cover
another your pattern if you will in
natural language and one of our
possibilities I think will be to look to
add framenet that is exactly such a
large inventory of of these things you
know I've I've wanted to do a projection
to frame that into Sumo for for several
decades now uh did some early work with
uh the team there and we we published uh
some some work about that in the mid
2000s but we didn't do a comprehensive
inventory of all of their different
frames and so I think there's a good
project there uh to to do a
more detailed exploration of all the
frames and frame that and translating
them to Sumo because the frames and
frame it don't have a precise logical
semantics which is one of the challenges
I think that people have found with
using that resource it's not anchored in
the same way that it needs to be I think
to be used more productively so so
there's I think an interesting project
there that would have a very practical
outcome
but for now I'm just going to talk about
the synthetic text is because we're not
even into that phase yet the synthetic
text is is the tough stuff we just
started this work uh sort of mid-fall
uh so that kind of gives you your
perspective on on where we are this is
going to be a long-term thing
so I tried to collect all of the things
that I thought I could detail both
linguistically and in Sumo so things
like uh propositional attitudes modals
tenses names and rules and basic forms
of transitive intransitive ditransitive
verbs in this subject verb object basic
a grammar of English
oh try to say what some of these things
are so I'm going to give you an example
it's it's a real example of stuff we can
generate and it looks kind of funny
because and I'll tell you why it looks
funny and what we what we can do to fix
it and uh it's other examples like it
um but I'm you know giving you words and
all of this extremely early uh research
even though I think it's very promising
I'm going to tell you what's wrong so
far in the examples show stuff that that
look kind of funny so you know an
internet user traps a crustacean that's
a pretty funny sentence it's
syntactically valid and I think you can
imagine an interpretation of that
sentence that's legitimate in the real
world okay I'm an internet user and I go
down to the beach and I catch a crab you
can imagine that actually happening but
I'm not sure you'd ever find that
sentence uttered by a person we think we
can do better constraining ultimately
our language generation through using
large language models uh it should be in
principle fairly easy to do so that we
we generate stuff that's just a little
bit more reasonable a little more common
a little more expected
um but this is what we've got right now
because we're just creating these
templates and we substitute in all of
the the legitimate possibilities were
legitimate it's just you know does it
meet syntactic and type constraints
specified by sumo and so it's possible
for an interview user to trap a
Crustaceans so we generate this sort of
thing amongst many other possibilities
and at the same time we generate the
logic expression that you see on the
left I'm sorry I'm throwing code at you
and I don't have uh the the time here to
go into the full syntax of this
expression with the moment this is just
first order logic so it's an existential
quantifier saying there exists an
internet user a trapping or an ambush is
the term that's used in Sumo again
remember labels and definitions are
different so we used a particular
software
identifier of Ambush but its definition
fits with what you would expect of
trapping okay and just the word that we
happen to be using in English is
trapping the software programming
language identifier we're using in the
Sumo library is Ambush okay so you
shouldn't expect those to be identical
because we have different labels for
things that we may have use consistently
in terms of their formal semantics but
their labels may vary
so we have an agent that does something
that agent is the internet user the
object of the action is the crustacean
um and the yeah the object of the action
is something and that something is a
crustacean all right so very simple
sentence very simple logic formalization
and so we generate tons of sentences
like this for
different objects and different agents
and different actions this is your most
most simple subject verb object sentence
and we have lots of different objects
that can play roles different agents
that can play roles and different
processes that are already defined in
Sumo so we just go through the entire
inventory and we also probabilistically
generate that we look at uh
each of these symbols in Sumo has a
connection to wordnet and wordnet has
word frequencies for each of those uh
those Concepts so by looking into
wordnet we can see which Concepts
formally Define Concepts in Sumo are
more likely to occur in free text
individually and so we do prioritize Our
Generation on the basis of trying to
make it more likely
using a randomizer in Java and then a
frequency table we try to make it more
likely that we generate sentences with
things that are more commonly seen But
as we can see the the even though
internet user may be fairly common
um in in natural language text you
wouldn't likely see it paired with
trapping or a crustacean and so it's
these pairwise selectional restrictions
that we don't have right now which is
why you get these funny combinations
uh we can generate times uh so we can
have the internet user trap station or
trap decoration or will trap or is
trapping and its formal temporal logic
expression one thing you often find in
simpler knowledge Expressions is verbs
used as predicates without tense so you
might have in a Knowledge Graph internet
user a relation trapping or traps of
some sort and then crustacean right this
would be a more typical expression in a
graph and that doesn't really capture
what the entire sentence is saying right
it says that there is a temporal
qualification to what this what is
happening in the sentence is happening
now right and so uh there's a begin fund
of this activity and an end function of
this activity and now is between those
two things you have a dike dick as we
say in linguistics right something
that's being referred to that gives
semantics to the sentence that's only
meaningful in the context of the speaker
and The Listener here they're now
Etc there's a lot of these things and
we've got to be able to handle that in
order to capture the semantics in a
sentence so it's not enough to say
there's a trapping relation between the
internet user and the crustacean we
really have to go to a temporal modal
logic Beyond first order logic with
equality to capture this information and
capture it in a way that's going to work
not just now for this one isolated case
but for all possible cases of these sort
of temporal Expressions it's also common
for people that don't have a background
in modal logic to sort of assume that
there's some kind of a fudge for this in
a graph representation there isn't right
and this is why logicians work on this
stuff it's hard getting it right has
taken many many decades of effort and so
you can fudge it but essentially
somewhere down the line you're going to
get completely wrong conclusions
nonsensical conclusions because you
don't have this same strength of
semantics in your representation that's
why we need this difficult and
expressive logic
we have negation negation is another big
problem for graphs right you've got to
be able to negate an arbitrary
conjunction or disjunction of other
statements to do that you've got to have
a construct that is beyond a particular
relation that is is a sort of a
contextualized relation it can handle a
whole expression logic already gives you
this and getting negation right is is
really a necessity in logic or in any
other representation you're trying to
create so like you sometimes people try
to say well I can do that in my graph or
I can do that in my description logic
and well maybe you can for this one
point case but essentially if you're
doing this in your ad hoc representation
that's not a formal expressive logic
you're going to wind up syntactically
recreating what logicians have already
done and done many years prior
and you're going to sort of discover
these things on a point by Point basis
instead of just getting them right from
the start so encourage people to to you
use a representation that can handle the
full complexity of the semantics of
English and only a higher order logic
will give you that
so here's case an internet user doesn't
trap a crustacean on negating this
entire complex existentially Quantified
expression that includes a temporal
motor logic expression within it
what if I have you know an agent Patrick
desires that the internet user trap a
crustacean pretty common to see in news
texts you know uh Kevin McCarthy said he
believes that the next vote for speaker
will be successful
um you know bolsonaro desires that he uh
be the leader of the country again
these are very common uh expressions in
natural language they are not infrequent
and they're difficult and they require
this sort of expressive logic and that's
the sort of thing that we're handling
we're able to generate this stuff and
have a representation that handles it
and then maybe if we're lucky have a
theorem prover that can handle it I mean
higher order logic theorem proving is
still difficult and somewhat
experimental and so that's a parallel
line of research
um but you know we're not sort of hand
waving away this problem we're not
imagining it doesn't exist or imagining
that we can really handle all this
complexity and language without uh this
this additional set of of computational
support that we believe is you know in
fact really required
uh so here just making the logic and the
sentence more and more difficult the
plumber knows that Patrick desires that
the internet user traps a crustacean you
know pretty artificial sounding sentence
admittedly but not all such constructs
uh for sentences are uh that that rare
right you do get in a news report
um The New York Times reported that uh
the speaker
desires that this bill pass without
further amendment that would not be a
particularly unusual sentence and yet it
follows exactly this pattern
so one of the things that we need to do
and if anyone is at all intrigued by
this work and thinking well how can I uh
contribute which would be wonderful uh
here's a great way to do that one thing
that is that we need that needs to be
added to sumo
and yet is also fairly well constrained
in terms of the the complexity of the
underlying axioms that need to be
expressed so it's possible to make these
fairly formulaic and in fact the use
that we make of them inside my Java code
that generates logic language pairs is
very formulaic and will look for only uh
axioms that that are of a very
particular restricted form in order to
do its restriction of which sentences
get generated
we have this notion of capability a
capability relation at Sumo so it says
that uh some kind of thing is capable of
Performing some kind of role in some
kind of action
so ears are capable of hearing guns are
capable of shooting and we have to talk
about things that might happen in order
to restrict the sentences that we
generate we'd like to be able to say
that John you know John it can't be
eating a boat dock we might generate
something like that now but we want to
be able to restrict eating to have an
object transferred or a resource that is
only food
ideally food for that particular animal
so we want termites to be able to eat
Boat Docks but we don't want Bob the
plumber to be able to eat a boat tuck
uh and we have a lot of processes and we
have a lot of objects in Sumo and so
creating an inventory of these different
capability Expressions would eliminate I
think a lot of the kind of funny
sounding sentences we generate now that
said I think it's not catastrophic that
we have some of these funny sentences
because remember that we're ultimately
trying to go from uh organically
occurring natural language text in the
wild in order into arbitrary logic
Expressions so the fact that we have
other sentences that kind of have a
similar form but don't really make a lot
of common sense may not be a big issue
because as long as we have enough
examples of things that are reasonable
that do cover the vocabulary we care
about that do have reasonable
selectional restrictions that that'll
still us enable us to translate the good
stuff that occurs the sensible sentences
into sensible logic expressions and the
fact that we have a corporate purpose of
translations where the translation is
reasonable but the core sentence is kind
of focus may just be background noise we
may be able to get away with that but
even if that proves not to be a problem
it still would be better for us to have
in Sumo these capability Expressions
just to add to our knowledge of how the
world works so if anybody is intrigued
by this I'd love to help you get started
because I think it would be not too hard
to do and would be of great value to the
project
so we have a lot of as I've said I've
said a couple times now that we have a
lot of processes we have a lot of
objects well what what do I mean by a
lot well here's uh just a segment of the
natural language comments on a portion
of the hierarchy starting from the top
here are all the process types in Sumo
we have 1300 of them at last count and
here are a number of
uh so in a lot of sentences we don't
restrict what processes can hold for a
given sentence and we'd like to have
again these selectional restrictions
based on capability expressions for the
type of objects that can participate in
the types of processes so we don't get
silly stuff
for each of these processes we have
mappings to verbs and wordnet so that's
what allows us to to cycle to iterate
through all the process types and still
generate a sentence not using the labels
in Sumo but rather using the labels the
legitimate words in the word net
dictionary so for example for Ambush
it's mapped to a particular numbered
synset a collection of synonyms
collection of synonymous words and
wordnet that linguistically identifies a
sense in English
and so we have Ambush that's mapped to
since set blah blah blah 926. uh it has
a certain definition has a certain set
of synonyms and buscade Ambush lying in
weight and a trap and that's why we saw
a trapping earlier the internet user
traps a crustacean that was exactly this
equivalent symbolt uh since that for
ambush
um we have lots of case rules so the way
these are the ways in which entities can
participate in events uh there are some
simple systems including some simple
systems in linguistics if you look at
uh I think verbnet has some of this set
of restrictions so agent patient
instrument resource these are very
common
um and so you'll also see Agent Zero
agent one sometimes as labels and
semi-formal Linguistics talking about
the roles that entities play in
activities
uh and so occasionally I've gotten this
question which I think is funny is like
well why isn't it enough to have just
agent patient and instrument well yes
that does cover at a high level maybe
exhaustibly uh the roles that things can
play I mean James pistiovsky also has
this set of qualier relations this is a
common uh I think approach in
linguistics to try to explain language
through a small number of covering
predicates or abstractions and while
that might be fine for abstract
Linguistics in practice there's a lot
more that we can say about the world
about how things interact in events that
happen and so we've come up with 67 of
them and I think this is you know many
orders of magnitude too small but it's a
good start that's the stuff that we've
found that's that's been useful over the
years so invading virus Cadillac
Catalyst broker enjoys reagent all of
these relate Nations and many of them
are sub relations of things like agent
and patient and instrument and resource
but they're more specific they they
entail different additional knowledge
when they're used and it's knowledge
which fits with our knowledge of the
real world
we have lots of objects so here's just
the corpuscular objects things that are
not substances that have Parts uh and we
have 930 of them a lot of them or
content bearing objects or things that
may have writing or symbols on them that
are are common in our world as well as
organic objects like organisms
um there's a lot of these and they all
play different roles in different
activities
uh here are some of the roles that uh
human beings or agents can play you know
you can have a certain profession you
can be a plumber or a programmer and you
can switch freely from one to the other
this you know past weekend and maybe my
toilet breaks and I have to be a plumber
today I'm a programmer uh maybe tonight
I will be teaching a course and so I'll
be a lecturer
um these different roles are free and uh
flexible and large and they also uh are
temporarily qualified right you can play
different roles at different times so
it's not enough to say as wordnet
unfortunately does as a linguistic
product that a sub type of human is
plumber well you can be a plumber one
time and not be a plumber another time
and that doesn't mean you cease to be a
human it's a bad relation to have
formally although it's a reasonable
relation to have linguistically because
you can do the substitution tests that
linguists do of substituting uh say a
super class for a subclass and it works
in a lot of sentences but it doesn't
work formally doesn't work in logic so
we need to separate out these roles and
say that they're transient temporally
qualified rules that people can have
so we can generate against bogus stuff
like Robert kills a boat dock doesn't
really make any sense it makes sense
syntactically but we need these
capability restrictions to handle them
and and a lot of times we do have
restrictions like the rule below here
um but that it's just I I can't afford
to do theorem proving while I'm doing
generation if I need to generate a one
terabyte Corpus of language logic pairs
I can't prove the truth of every
sentence this would take you know many
years if just to do one run of the
generation system I've got to find a way
to optimize that and the way to optimize
it is just to look at capability
Expressions even though the the
following rule that I'm showing up here
says that the killing has to have an
object that's an organism and a boat
dock is not an organism so each this
would be trapped if I could do fear
improving for everything I generate but
I just don't have time so I need to use
this more restrictive form that I can
turn into a sort of a lookup table and
and make run much faster
okay so I need this following expression
that uh if there's a capability of
killing the uh killing event uh only the
patient has to be an organism if it's
the patient or the object of the killing
event it must be an organism
I also had the the question of how much
is too much you know right now I am
generally able to generate say a
terabyte uh Corpus in the span of a
couple of hours
and then train on it uh training takes
about 28 hours on a multi-gpu fairly
beefy server
um how much is too much I don't have a
sense of that how much is it too little
you know we're getting a good Fidelity
you know we break things up in the
standard uh uh
crane test uh
split
um but and we get good metrics you know
we get a perplexity score that's down
around 1.01 1.02 uh it's one reasonable
measure for the Fidelity of your deep
neural network training approach
um but is that good enough I I don't
know yet we just need to do a lot more
experiments so we have about a hundred
names that we use so we have a corpus of
of common human names we have about
these 300 rules we have lots of
different propositional ad attitudes
Each of which could be negated we have
modals like handmade should that are
also formally expressed in our modal
logic those in turn could be negated we
have 400 different sorts of roles like
plumber and teacher
300 processes those in fast could be
negated and we have past present future
and then the progressive tense for each
of those all those possibilities we've
got 930 direct corpuscular objects and
then we've got substances which I
haven't listed on here we've got lots of
substances like water or gasoline
67 case rules and again 930 of those
same corpuscular objects that can be
indirect objects
and then I've also added a bunch of
politeness expressions like can I may I
should uh do the following so a lot of
these modal Expressions can can be
become politeness so please may I Etc so
we can handle stuff in uh chatbot or
conversational kind of stuff that's
that's very commonly seen so I did an
inventory of stuff that a lot of the
chat Bots use for their sentence
patterns to make sure we cover that but
a lot of these combinations are nonsense
so I've got to somehow pair it down if
not if it's not a problem in terms of
creating a lot of junk that can
otherwise get ignored when I'm
translating a sentence at the very least
it slows down training and so as I make
the Corpus larger I I have to Pare down
the nonsense just so that my training
phase is is possible because I don't
have the resources of open AI to spend
three million dollars a month on running
their you know chat GPT for the world
right I've got to run on one server that
my friend Prague has access to
um so there's lots more that I can still
do uh units and measures I've only begun
starting to do that I've got a little
bit of that so I can say you know uh you
know Bob puts uh three three birds in
his wagon uh uh or three uh pounds of
steak in his jar something of that sort
uh because we've got a whole set of I
think they're about 60 different system
international uh units and Sumo has them
all and then of course your values can
be within all sorts of different ranges
we've got logical combinations of
sentences that I could generate so Bob
goes to the store hand Bob buys cookies
um we can temporarily qualify all of
these things I've got a little bit of
that already so you know Bob goes to the
store on Tuesday Bob goes to the store
on January 27th of 2003.
uh we have a bit of an issue that a lot
of these case rules require different
prepositions so I don't have those
working correctly I need to actually do
a whole set of patterns that are a
little fragment of frame net if you will
for uh different action types and which
particular prepositions are historically
used so you get in the car you get on
the boat you go to the station I don't
handle all of those correctly
things we can do like with more than one
agent right now agents are always
singular in my examples we can certainly
have Jack and Jill go up the hill and
not just Jack I do have now just
implemented quotes for said so we can
handle the common this common form for
news reports or novels or what have you
lots more things that can be done to
make this a more comprehensive Corpus
long before I you know run out of stuff
to do I I can cover a lot larger portion
or subset of of English
um so here's some just some detail on
how we run the model
um I just got a script it's not too hard
uh just takes a long time
so future work uh once I get done
exhausting the set of things I can think
of that I can do then we need to start
seeing where it fails on natural texts a
big thing to do is to use either word to
VEC or some large language model maybe
as a way to Pare down the number of
nonsensical combinations along with my
preferred approach of having a lot more
capability senses which will then add to
the understanding the the competence of
this core model regardless of whether
we're trying to do language
understanding or some other kind of
project and I really want to do a
comprehensive test on the the baby
Corpus to just see if I can do better if
I'm not learning and teaching the
machine Learning System how to do
inference but using a system that
already knows how to do inference I
think I should be able to get better
scores but that remains a empirical
question if I can do that I think maybe
then people pay more attention to this
work so it would be a nice demo
okay that's that's it so thanks for
learning about this early work as well
as the more mature model that it's based
on that's already being applied
commercially and lo would love it if I
got somebody on this call so excited
that you wanted to do some work together
excellent thank you for the presentation
Adam
you can unshare or leave it up and we
will begin with Dave providing some
initial comments and questions
yes one uh idea can you hear me now I
can great one idea that occurred to me
several points during your presentation
was if you put part of the training a
part of the pruning inside the modern
by creating persistent agents with goals
and beliefs
Bob isn't just a transient pattern of
activations but Bob is something that
stays around for a while and perhaps
Bob's desires evolve more slowly than
Bob's beliefs including Bob he believes
about Carol and Carol's relevance and
whether Carol believes correct things
about what he's interested in right now
have you gotten her out of something as
as Charming as that
well that's what the baby folks did
right they they've got this model World
model and they generate sentences and
variations of those sentences based on
that world model and we could certainly
re-implement what they've the simple
system that they've done in Lua
um in a more complicated blocks world if
you will that uses all the entities and
objects that are in Sumo that's
something I'd like to do uh I can only
okay reconnecting here
foreign
thank you
we've got Daniel back
I had to move to a backup
um source
for a strange reason but let us continue
the conversation with uh no video
and uh yes the last thing you added was
the capacities and the opportunity to
contribute there
please feel free to pick up there or I
can pick up there and take it in a
different direction
yeah David I was just uh talking a
little bit further about uh maybe some
other work that's going on in uh
psychology and uh ontologies emotions
and I was just commenting how
um Sumo already has an extensive
ontology of emotions but of course it
has ontologies of many other things so
anybody that wanted to study a
representation of emotion for use in
Psychotherapy or any other reason we'd
kind of get for free all of this other
stuff defining a model of the rest which
would I think make that work have a
greater impact over time it'd be more
readily adoptable in different contexts
because it has this link to a whole host
of other semantic defined entities
yeah one of the things that would make
it a lot easier too to to
participate across groups is if it were
easier to actually run Sigma several of
us have tried to install and run it I
don't know that anybody in the active
inference uh group has ever succeeded uh
you do put for the for the the
appropriate environment you have some
really nice videos and I've tried to
follow those in every case it broke down
with some warning like uh if you keep
going your Windows system May
self-destruct why don't you stop now uh
so it's pretty scary we even tried to go
to a um a vendor a provider of cloud
services items like Sumo at all that
provide rigor in how those different
state spaces get translated and mapped
to each other like short text to long
text long text to short text short text
to Mouse movement although those
different mappings are implausible in
multiple ways without a formal semantics
the kind that you're describing
yeah
yeah I agree
maybe I could say a word about about
uncertain reasoning
um because this is an area that I think
a lot of people that are used to being
in a probabilistic representation
often have some misconceptions about
what's possible in logic usually based
on the fact that the the logic that most
people are exposed to
academically is going to be first order
logic where you do have just truth
values binary truth values right it's
either true or false and people want to
be able to represent things that are
uncertain or likely or unlikely and
therefore assume that uh that logic
can't handle that and well it can it's
just you have to go beyond first order
logic and so that's exactly why we're in
the realm of higher order logic and Sumo
and have modal expressions
we want to be able to say and can say in
the logic that something is likely or
that one thing is more likely than
another or that because of such and such
event something has become more likely
so we have to make a projection that
includes some temporal reasoning as well
so logic is uh you know you could call
it a non-classical logic right
I find that a little uncomfortable
because most non-classical Logics are
things like you know four valued Logics
or uh things that don't just have true
and faults well motologics do still just
have true and false but they are able to
describe an entire situation sort of
with all its possibilities and
conditionals possible things like
possible worlds which allow us to
capture some of these same intuitions
that a probabilistic representation like
Bayesian reasoning can't
is I think there's a to my mind a clear
advantage of the symbolic representation
it
it it is possible of course uh to have
large libraries of empirical data
to have uh
realistic probability assessments and
say that you know such and such an event
is 73 likely in this context
but a lot of times when I see people
using probabilistic orbasian
representations they're sort of using
them mathematics is precise thus the
source data is often not precise people
are making a guess you know I guess that
it's probably 70 percent likely that the
following will happen then they encode
that in their system and I think those
things are better represented as
symbolic preferences so this is more
likely than that but we don't know that
it's 73
likely versus 56 percent likely
an additional problem I think often not
maybe not in your case but in certainly
in many cases with people they're doing
numeric probabilities is that the
numeric probabilities force a total
order essentially
um and you've got these appearance of of
precision where 73 is more likely than
56 but in reality if that comes from
anything less than statistically
rigorous empirical data then it's just
sort of a confidence Factor like was
used in a lot of old style expert
systems that that doesn't give you
reliable results so none of those
criticisms may actually apply to your
situation I don't have enough detail
about what you're doing but I would ask
you to consider those points
awesome I'll give a thought on that and
then Dave happy day hear from it
so for any given model architecture
symbolically represented like a symbolic
regression or a Bayesian graph
constraining on that model structure
which in the variational inference world
we just call Q it's just the variational
distribution
the one that we are getting to choose
the family that we're parameterizing it
from so it's like our designer symbolic
model and why the data come in so then
free energy which is the imperative for
minimization whether it's the real-time
variational free energy happening right
now or it's the
planned or anticipated expected free
energy
in either of those cases
for a given generative model given Q
distribution and given set of data you
might have a very high confidence in
something that was very inadequate and
so in that way it's like there are
distributions of Scatter Plots that can
confuse a least squares regression or
you get some sort of misleading model
outcome and it may even be invisible you
may be able to look at Diagnostics of
the linear regression and tell that some
sort of error or aberration is happening
but you also may not like a kind of
unknown unknowns question and in the
case of cognitive modeling
these State spaces can be very large and
they're often trained with sparse data
so this problem of overfitting and
conditional and dynamic relationships so
that something can be like true and
trained upon for 100 video frames and
then something changes and then there's
a non-linear change in what can happen
next or how things unfold through time
so that's kind of like the complexity of
action
and
perhaps could you speak to how action is
represented or treated or how the
concept of action
selection and planning and strategy and
implementation impact how did these
features develop in Sumo Through Time
I think there was more to that question
it sounds like Daniel's maybe have still
having some connectivity that was it
just how did the concept of action
evolve Through Time
how does the concept yeah
um let's say uh there was a lot packed
into your question I'm not sure I I
grasped most of it but let me let me
just maybe make a I'll give myself a
related question
which is uh how do we handle the fact
that sometimes a machine Learning
Systems the mathematics has such
linearities that we get nonsensical
conclusions
right I think that's a fairly common
problem
um so I think that the interaction
between these two models of the world
the statistically machine learning
derived model
and the symbolic model is really
important so that our machines don't go
off the rails as it were I'm using a
tournament called cognitive guard rails
and I think this applies well to people
you know people have instinctive
reactions to many things and we have at
the same time a deliberative cognitive
mind that constrains those reactions we
might react emotionally and react badly
to something that sort of triggers Us in
some way but then we have another
process in our head that says well you
know we're in a social situation and so
no I don't want to punch this person
that's offended me even though I might
be tempted to do so
um if we have a self-driving car that
sees an object in front of it my initial
reaction might to be to plow through it
but the cost to doing so might be very
high so maybe I want to Swerve or break
gradually
and having this interaction between
these two models I think can address
some of this problem that we see uh with
non-linearities of modern machine
learning systems that do you know work
really well in a lot of common cases and
then sometimes just Veer off into
Infinity as it were and do something
completely ridiculous
yes I I appreciate that response I think
it's exactly like you described with the
overfitting to the meaning and going off
the rails from a cognitive perspective
is there's like the known unknowns as an
example especially there's a University
of Wyoming I think did a nice paper
maybe quite a while back now probably at
least five years back that
you would say yes it's a cat or a dog
because it was just training on sort of
a coincidental uh feature of pixels that
maybe approximated the fur of the animal
and so it couldn't recognize a uh you
know recognized a test pattern as being
a cat and it couldn't recognize a simple
cartoon drawing as a cat because it'd
never seen anything like that and wasn't
looking at the essential features of the
world
and so machines are really great at
finding correlations but that doesn't
mean they're the right correlations I
think that's at the root of a lot of
things that we call
uh uh over training or overfitting
um but we never know really whether it's
it's fit correctly or overfit I mean
there's sure there's some some numeric
measures that at times can tell you okay
we're we're bouncing out of this local
minimum and and our our uh our Fidelity
has gone down numerically but we don't
know what that really means in respect
to the common sense larger world that is
represented by something that's much
larger than any given test set that we
might be training on so I think that
having a sort of diff completely
different representation of the world
can help guard against some of this and
so I thought of using machine learning
and symbolic systems together where the
symbolic system uh
addresses problems in the input data
right by because in faulty input data
erroneous input data is is always a big
problem how do we know we're training on
the right stuff how do we know that if
we're training on a uh a system to
diagnose uh check fraud for example or a
credit card fraud that we don't have uh
some bogus data that's crept in here
there that might have a spurious
correlation we've got say zeroed out
fields or a field of 99 it's really as a
don't care field but it's in the data
and there's no easy way for us to
discover it if we've got terabytes of
data wouldn't it be nice to have a a
common sense system that could act like
an intern a human intern working at warp
speed looking over our all of our input
data to make sure we've uh not included
any inputs that are at odds with what we
know about the real world and then on
the output side making
a few
inferences in our symbolic system could
help the overall computational system
not make really dumb conclusions like oh
let we don't know what that things is so
let's run over it might be the
conclusion that that a statistical
system has but we'd like to have our our
combined agent uh be able to trap things
like that in the same way that a person
wouldn't presumably punch somebody else
who's offended him because they know
that that's both illegal and immoral
thanks Dave do you want to add or ask
something
yeah a couple of the other approaches
that sometimes simplify exactly these
same kind of problems that that Daniel
and Adam have both been coming through
uh one is fuzzy logic
uh sometimes a fuzzy solution and a
probability probabilistic solution agree
numerically
but in other situations they don't and
in many of those cases the fuzzy answer
turns out to be way back when Lefty's
out exifying and reacting to situations
and it wasn't until he started calling
the logic fuzzy that people were beating
on him he was just coming up with a
great results
another
um
approach that that's been impressing me
uh is uh David Deutsch and Kiera
marletto's work in Constructor Theory
where they start by asking what can be
done and what can't be done
and what does it mean to do something
what does it mean to be able to
construct
um
they generalize the notion of uh
catalysts for instance as as a general
Concept in systems theory and um
they just identified I'll know a lot of
things that people spend a lot of brain
power on is just simply being
nonsensical
you can't construct that therefore
you're wasting your time if you try to
work out how it could be done would be
done with the consequences where if it
could be done it just can't be so go on
to something interesting
well I'm not familiar with the latter
work but I am a bit familiar with fuzzy
logic and maybe I should just mention it
you know this has been another thing
where people that are familiar with
fuzzy logic wonder how you could do this
in a non-fuzzy logic
and
the the challenge then comes down to
again uh people that aren't familiar
with Logics Beyond first order a lot of
things we might say about like you know
John John is tall okay
um and maybe John how do we how do we
compute whether John is tall and we have
this problem of well if in a traditional
logic system there who would have the
problem that okay if he's above six feet
he's 12 he's below six feet he's tall
therefore if he's you know five feet 11
and 7 8 inches he's not tall and of
course we all know from a common sense
Point standpoint that's ridiculous and
so we'd want to use fuzzy logic but in
fact what we should be able to say is
that he's tall with respect to a
particular group
right and if we can make these more
complex statements generally involving
sets of things and conditionals that are
you know beyond first order logic we can
express these things perfectly well in
in this more expressive logic we don't
always have to go to fuzzy logic because
one of the challenges that I think if
you have with fuzzy logic is again a lot
of people that did work in this sort of
world back you know like almost 30 years
ago I think came up with things that
were functioning well empirically as
sort of hacks because they didn't have
uh data about you know what is the
actual statistical value curve of
tallness it was just somebody's guess
about what the curve of tallness
membership should be for example so I'd
like uh the the notion of fuzzy logic
intuitively I'm not sure that I care for
it so much on on a theoretical basis and
on a practical basis there's simply
another way to do it
very interesting Dave want to add
anything
yeah now this is
um if we have time for this this is
we're a much deeper question about the
way the Sumo rules are written
is do we have time to go in in a lot of
depth in this venue
depth not necessarily breath not
necessarily a big answer but okay I'll
just ask this uh reading through the the
rules a number of rules have
conditions that very specifically asked
in the first participant of a relation
if the following holds then the
following logic Applause if a different
set of conditions on the
paid recipient of action the indirect
object or direct object of a process
holds then you can apply the following
logic and you know I look at that and I
say wait a minute these are split these
different rules are splitting off very
different kind of real world situations
within the same Sumo class
well there's got to be two things have
to be true in order to do that in order
to have find these differentiating rules
within a single class first you call
those by the same name
in whatever natural languages you were
thinking in when you wrote the rules
and second the formal
literally the abstract algebra of these
various cases have to all be analogous
they all have to be isomorphic
and my name for that situation is you're
covering analogical cases in the same
Sumo class and in that sense the Sumo
class itself is an analogy it's an
analogy among these various cases which
in different domains of apparition
am I just not thinking
discerningly enough about what a Sumo
class represents or can assume across
actually be a higher or analogy
um there's it's hard for me to know
because I mean there's no analogical
reasoning happening so I'm not sure
you're talking about analogies and
there's no natural language happening
once you're in the formal system so I'm
not sure why you mentioned natural
language I think we'd have to look at a
very specific example and then you know
we could we could run it on run run that
example on a theorem pervert and you'd
see exactly how things behave it's not
something about you know classes per se
um you know you just mentioned how how
do rules work in a logic right you've
got preconditions uh for the antecedent
of a rule and you've got the consequent
of a rule and yes indeed the the the
symbols in that formal system have to
match that's that's how logic works
right I'll get some specific examples of
an email empty okay sounds great
in our last minutes here and also
apologies for the internet disrupt
um this is part of our long-term
Journey learning about this and applying
it to active inference so we're going to
keep this thread alive and be able to
bring some more informed uh areas of
intersection and application but one
that I wanted to mention was to return
to your type 1 type 2 thinking
and the way that there's a faster
reflexive or habitual
statistical type 1 inference and then a
slower type 2 what you refer to as
deliberate and deductive that involves
symbolic logic and in chapter 5 of the
active inference textbook there's a
schematic of a dopaminergic
neural circuit in the Central and
peripheral nervous system where there's
a dopamine related parameter
computationally that's like a dial in
the model that is controlling the
balance between replicating actions
according to the prior like just the
Habit so it's some distribution of
capacities affordances and then if
there's three options it's 0.8
0.1.1 so then under the most habitual
setting like what we might even call
non-agentic or subconscious then that
Vector of affordances is recapitulated
in action selection and then
in a different dopaminergic regime there
is increasingly fine scale and
potentially overfit
application of the free energy and that
can reflect like a symbolically informed
deep generative model of the world which
captures semantics of the world like
nested time scales and temporal priority
effects so it's interesting that the
this area while deep hierarchical
generative models often are described as
if they have semantic value however that
is usually just sort of specified or
only explored in a few limited cases so
integrating and working at that mapping
between the top down symbolic and the
bottom-up data driven is going to be a
really important interesting area so as
a closing round or question
what do you see in the ecosystem and or
what directions if you didn't State them
earlier you're working on
this year
well yeah the generative AI stuff
certainly got a huge amount of press
um it's it's fascinating as an
intellectual exercise certainly and and
it's fascinating to have a systems that
can complete sentences and write stories
and you know always have an answer to a
question but as we're seeing with a lot
of newer things that are that are being
written as follow-ups to all the
excitement that people are showing how
well these these systems will give you
an answer but it's often a complete
hallucination right I saw one recently
of saying well you know Hillary Clinton
was the 43rd president
um
well it came up with that somehow by
merging together various texts that
other people have written but it doesn't
make sense together it's not true
right
um and so I I think these systems are
interesting in the way that a a parrot
can have a very limited conversation you
know you can teach your parrot how to
say Polly want a cracker and say thank
you when you give it a cracker that
doesn't mean it actually understands
anything about what it's doing it's just
a stimulus response
um now first there is the philosophical
question if the stimulus response uh
pairing is complicated enough well isn't
aren't human beings also just
collections of stimulus and response so
that that may be true but I don't think
we're at that level of complexity yet
for our machines and I think some of the
things that we can get these generative
models to do they're so obviously
nonsensical human or good evidence that
uh they're they're certainly not uh
sentient and they're not even smart and
they're certainly not very reliable if
we have uh very challenging or higher
high criticality tasks to worry about I
think they'll be useful in the same way
that Google search is useful it doesn't
always get the right answer it will
universally get many wrong answers but
it's very powerful and useful tool when
you have a human being available to
filter out all the nonsense and just uh
use that as a filter for what what
they'd otherwise have to do you know
it's not feasible for a human being to
answer question by reading all the books
in the library but if Google can give
you 10 books and 10 pages in those 10
books where your answer may be found
it's done you a great service even
though it's given you you know Winnie
the Pooh along with the handbook of
analytical or organic chemistry or
something where you're at your actual
answer is found
so in that same way chat gbt might be
very useful in breaking your writer's
block to help write the summary for a
proposal or a student essay but you
certainly don't want to have it write
the whole essay for you and hand it in
because you'll probably fail
um so I'm not quite as worried about uh
high school or college essays as some
commentators have have been I think
it'll be a useful partner and that's
about all and we've got to understand
these limitations and ideally pair it
with a symbolic system that really knows
something about the real world so that
they can work together
awesome
Dave first and then Adam
what are your closing thoughts or
reflections
I've enjoyed this very much uh we've got
lots of work to to plow forward and do
I'm glad there's going to be common work
that uh
we can become affordances for one
another on thank you gentlemen
well thank you Dave for you know good
questions good comments and and Daniel
as well and and for setting this up
um I guess I would encourage you know
what I've maybe encouraged in the past
is a lot of the things that that we've
talked about in these several
conversations we've had are
General right uh you know we're saying
what's an overarching direction for the
field or something and I think that if
we got down into some real specific
examples and actually doing some
representation together
um then a lot of these uh more
philosophical Notions would go away and
we'd get down to doing something that
has has practical utility that's why I
also encourage uh actually having you
know if people do say some of the Sumo
exercises together because I think gave
some of the questions that you were
having over you know what what is the
rule how is it working
um I can answer all those questions and
give you some very precise experience
that would give you a a real actual
understanding of how logic works and how
Sumo Works uh if we took the time
together to go through those exercises
do some work with the theorem improver
and it would clear up I think a lot of
maybe misunderstandings or
misconceptions and and give us a real
path to do something concrete together
because all the Talking is is great fun
it's the the doing and writing of
practical computational system that
hopefully we'll all want to get to
yes and say let us descend into the
particular
yes that's great I love it
great ending the Stream